here is some advice I would give to my
younger self when I was learning to code
Nicolas you may or may not know I have
been programming since I was a kid more
than 15 years ago I taught myself how to
code because I wanted to hack into
computers I never wanted to be a
developer I just wanted to learn how to
break into things and today I am a full
stock developer that has made a lot of
mistakes I spent time learning some
things that have proven useless to my
career today because I didn't know
myself well enough and I also wish I
learned other things sooner things that
I overlooked but are very important for
a career in software development and two
star here are the two most important
things I will tell to my younger self
number one time is your most valuable
asset and number two you need to know
yourself I personally Define wealth not
as how much money you have in your bank
account but as how much time you have
you can be the CEO of a company and own
a million cars and apartments but if you
don't have the time to sit with your
wife or with your friends then you are
poor in my eyes no one can buy more time
the clock ticks for everyone whether you
are musk or besos knowing yourself will
save you time and it will put you closer
to your goal and knowing yourself will
make the learning process better because
you will realize that you don't have to
learn everything that is to learn if you
know where you're going for example if
you know you want to make a video games
and that is your passion then you're
going to avoid JavaScript and Go full on
C plus plus in a real engine or if you
like iOS and apple and you want to make
beautiful applications for the iPhone
then you're going to go straight to
Swift or if you want to build products
you want to make your own startup that
you're going to have to learn JavaScript
and any other backend language that you
like or if you believe that blockchain
and web3 is the future like I do then
you're going to go full on and learn
roast goal and solidity there are a lot
of languages a lot of courses and books
you need to be selective you need to
know what to learn but also what not to
learn I did not know myself so I spent
time learning a wide array of topics
which made my progress slow there are so
many areas in software development that
is impossible to learn them all but of
course most people don't know themselves
and if you are like me and see all those
options maybe a website a video game or
an iOS application they all excite you
so what to do what language to start
with for beginners I think there are two
options on one hand there is Python and
on the other one there's JavaScript and
depending on what kind of person you are
one is better than the other if you are
a visual person if you like to build
interactive things maybe websites maybe
apps even video games things that people
can click on basically user facing
products then I would go for JavaScript
or if you are amazed by AI automation
trading Bots data mining then python is
your friend python is especially easy
for beginners because the syntax is very
very easy to write and understand but
having said this I wish JavaScript was
the first programming language I learned
because it allowed me to build so many
user facing products from websites to
apps backends and video games by the way
I made two free Javascript and python
courses that you can take right now by
clicking on the link below another thing
that I wish I did sooner was to
specialize in one programming language
it doesn't really matter what language
it is but choosing one programming
language that you like and trying to
learn it really well going deep and
mastering it is better than knowing many
languages shallowly by books on the
language read the best practices on that
language engage with the community of
the language and even go to a couple of
conferences it doesn't really matter
what language it is because after you
master one language moving to another
language will be super easy at the end
most programming languages are very
similar but it's important to be a
specialist on something hopefully you
choose a language that has a high demand
on the industry you choose to work with
another thing that I wish I did sooner
was to study the boring stuff like data
structures and algorithms this is
something that many sales thought
developers lack and that is because it's
like doing leg work at the gym mainskip
legday because it sucks and they prefer
doing biceps instead when learning to
code it's easy to focus on learning the
flashy parts and avoid the legwork it's
more fun to follow a tutorial that shows
you how to make real time video games
rather than reading a book to understand
the time and space complexity of
different sorting algorithms data
structures and algorithms are what takes
you to the next level they are what
allows you to optimize your applications
when things don't run as fast as they
should they are also what allows you to
ride clean and organized code now having
said this I am glad I didn't learn data
structures and algorithms too early when
I was learning to code when you're
starting learning the theory might be
frustrating and boring and since you
haven't built anything yet you might
have a hard time under understanding
where are you going to apply all these
Concepts that you're learning because of
this if you are a beginner focus on
making things first if you can make a
product with a front-end backend
database user authentication and you can
deploy that product to a server on AWS
then it's time to learn data structures
and algorithms not too early but not too
late another thing I wish I learned
sooner was SQL at some point in time
even if you are using an amazing
framework that hides it from you you are
going to need to talk to a database
directly and chances are that it will be
an SQL database SQL is very easy to
learn it's not that fun but is very very
useful you also don't need to learn a
ton of it I think that in two Sunday
afternoons you can earn as much SQL as
you need to survive outside of
programming languages learn to become
productive in your text editor I don't
care what it is I personally use Visual
Studio code because I think it's amazing
but no matter what you are using spend
some time customizing and becoming more
productive on it I don't mean changing
the colors or icons I mean learning the
keyboard shortcuts and the extensions
that will make you more productive and
save you time and last but not least
kill your ego especially as you gain
experience ego is the enemy ego will
stop you from growing ego will fool you
and tell you that you know enough that
there is nothing else to learn and that
you are at the Top If you want to be a
good developer a good programmer you
have to always stay a student you should
be always humble enough to ask questions
you need to know that there is always
something that you can learn you need to
know that anyone can teach you something
and you must remember how once you also
wear a beginner as well you need to be
able to adapt to constant change ask the
people that used to be Masters at Flash
and actionscript or the ones that used
to use Dreamweaver to build their
websites it's adapt or die please don't
become the senior developer that refuses
to learn something new because it means
learning from somebody younger than them
this is some of the advice I would like
to give to my younger self and I hope
that you find it useful in your journey
as well I also made a roadmap of this
specific programming languages and
Frameworks I would learn in which order
so if you are interested on a video like
that then please leave a like And
subscribe and we're gonna make it happen
now let me know in the comments what
advice would you give to your younger
self related to programming or not I'm
very curious it doesn't matter just let
me know in the comments I'm going to be
looking at them right now as always
thank you for watching and don't forget
if you want to learn to code and you
want to do it for free click the link
below and I will see you there stay free
stay happy see you in the next one bye
[Music]